A Guide to the Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1831 September 25 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the dangerous illness of her newborn baby, his recovery, Hannah Stearns arrival in Boston, her regret over the harsh measures enacted against Virginia slaves due to the Southampton insurrections, her confidence in the fidelity of Albemarle slaves, her gladness that her children will be raised far from that moral evil, the visit of two Frenchmen to Boston, the Counts [Alexis de] Toqueville and Beaumont [de la Bonniniere], and other visitors
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1831 October 27 (Box 3)
  discusses the drowning of Nat Turner, her fear that the editor [William Lloyd Garrison] of the Liberator and Walker's pamphlet were trying to repeat the scenes of St. Domingo in Virginia by their support of the rebellion, her belief they would accomplish more good by raising subscriptions throughout the Union for the purchase and emancipation of slaves, refers to the laws passed removing privileges formerly extended to slaves and making their lives harsher and more restricted, describes her new residence in Washington at the corner of Pennsylvania Avenue, I Street, and 20th Street, and mentions that Lewis now has a position in the State Department
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1831 November 20 (Box 3)
  sends news of little Ellen's delicate state of health, her other children, Boston, fashions, and the memoirs of Gouverneur Morris
- Martha Randolph and Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge [1832?] February 7 (Box 3)
  describes the busy routine and the crowded condition of their new house, excuses their sloth in answering her letters, describes Ben's practice in Halifax County, near Danville, reports on George, describes a fancy ball they plan to attend in Washington with details of costumes they were planning to wear, and mentions the birth of Browse Trist to Virginia and Nicholas
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1832?] March 7 (Box 3)
  assures her of how much they look forward to a visit from her in the summer, and sends news of the community
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1832 March 18 (Box 3)
  replies that she could not justify a visit to Boston this summer unless it would be to return little Nell after a visit with them in Washington, describes the fancy ball they attended at Commodore [Daniel Todd?] Patterson's, noting that the President did not approve of the ball and none of his family attended, and mentions their late loss, the death of Aunt Jane
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1832 April 4 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the plan of Frank Gray and Stuart Newton to visit Washington, and the news of her children and friends
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1832 June 5 (Box 3)
  discusses an exhibition in the Boston Athenaeum and her enthusiasm for the poetry of William Cullen Bryant whose book Poems(1832) she could not get a copy
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1832 June 11 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the death of little Bessie [Elizabeth Bulfinch Coolidge (1827-1832)], and his plans to go to Canton, China for 18 months for business purposes
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1832 June 21 (Box 3)
  urges Ellen to come and visit with her whole family to escape the epidemic of cholera at Quebec and Montreal carried to Boston by people fleeing the disease, and includes a sketch of the location of her residence in Washington
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1832 June 25 (Box 3)
  urges a visit to Edgehill and Virginia for their health, and sends news of Elizabeth Eppes
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1832 June 29 (Box 3)
  begs Martha to come to Boston to comfort Ellen especially because he will be away in China, mentions that his family is at the seashore, and assures her that he has not made his decision to travel to China hurriedly without careful thought
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1832 November 2 (Box 3)
  writing from Boston, she informs him about his family, Martha's meeting of the Audubons on the steamboat and their visit to Boston
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1833 January 22 (Box 3)
  describes the effect of the deaths of Clementine Vail and Harriet [Randolph?] upon her mother, mentions the lack of communication from Joseph that may last until April, tells of another family, the Forbes, whose youngest brother and son was in Canton
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1833 May 31 (Box 3)
  relates the forlorn emotions experienced since her mother left Boston a week ago, the receipt of a long letter from Joseph who described his voyage to Canton, his meeting with a traveler who resided in Borneo for two years, the receipt of his journal of about 100 pages describing his journey, and her hatred of the cold weather
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1833 June 10 (Box 3)
  describes the tonsillectomy procedure used on Martha [Trist], sends news of Lewis' intention to marry [Margaret G.] Meade, mentions her original opposition to the marriage of Jefferson Randolph to Jane Hollins Nicholas and how mistaken she was, the financial condition of the family since Nicholas received an appointment of a consulship and his salary as a clerk has stopped, sends her regards to friends in Boston, and mentions the death of Senator [Josiah] S. Johnston (1784-1833), who perished in the explosion aboard the steamship Lioness on the Red River, near Alexandria, Louisiana, and his poor wife Eliza Sibley
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1833 June 17 (Box 3)
  writes concerning her disappointment with the house in Newton and her intention of moving as soon as possible, the rambunctious activities of her children, a report of Joseph in good spirits and health while busy at Canton, and news of her friends in Boston and their children
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1833 June 24 (Box 3)
  describes the financial worries of her family, Nicholas' appointment as Consul to Havana (April 1833), the presence of sixteen or seventeen grown persons in the household, the family's disappointment with the financial terms of the consulship given to Nicholas, how her debts forced her to sell two slaves, the death of Charles Bankhead, the engagement of Lewis and Margaret G. Meade of Philadelphia
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1833 July 15 (Box 3)
  describes her visit with Martin Van Buren who related the details of the President's visit to Boston and Ellen's opportunity to meet him while he was there, the good impression made by the Yankees upon the President, her household servants and tribulations, the cost of running the household, and rumors of what life will be like in Cuba for Nicholas and his family
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1833 July 21 (Box 3)
  informs her mother that the sale of the paintings brought about $450.00, urges her to use the proceedings for her personal needs as the amount would hardly matter to Thomas Jefferson's creditors, asks for instructions about the money, lists the works of art that she kept back from the sale including the Ariadne, the [Napoleon ?] Bonaparte, the Holy Family, the Crucifixion, the Andromache, and the soap- stone Indian, with prices listed for the sale of some of the paintings, declares that the success of the sale was due mostly to the hard work of Thomas Bulfinch, and reveals her plans to move from Newton to Cohasset
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1833 September 15 (Box 3)
  writes concerning George who has received his sailing orders to report to Norfolk on the fifteenth to sail to the West Indies on the USS Vandalia flagship, Jefferson's determination to leave Virginia and go to Missouri due to the hostility of many in the state against him and his family, the huge debt remaining from his grandfather's estate, which he would pay by selling his farm, and the prejudice of the Methodist and Presbyterian ministers against him, about which Martha says "I think with him [Jefferson] Virginia is no longer a home for the family of Thomas Jefferson - the days of her glory are gone by, with Mr. Madison the last of her sons worthy the name will have passed away," notes that the monument to be erected over the grave of Thomas Jefferson is finished and the money from the sale of the paintings from Monticello will pay for it, that Monticello is again on the market, its environs totally altered, with the trees cut down, and the yard planted in corn, that Jefferson's concern for his slaves led him to consider Missouri as a new home because he could take them with him instead of selling them, and that Jeff's children have a new governess
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1833 October 27 (Box 3)
  expresses her disappointment over Ellen's decision not to spend the winter with them, describes the family's plans to stay with Jefferson until April or May when Nicholas returns home, to save on expenses, Mary's preparations to join Ellen in Boston, the purchase of "Carlton" by Alexander Rives, the visit of Mr. Hart of New York who claimed to represent a group of gentlemen determined to purchase Monticello for Martha Randoloph, the price Dr. Barclay is asking for Monticello and 230 acres of land, the utter ruin of Monticello under his ownership, the claim by Hart that Barclay showed him the original manuscript of Notes on Virginia which was missing from Jefferson's papers
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge [1833] December 2 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the increase of Ben's medical practice, who has assumed a great deal of Dr. Bramham's patients, George Carr's injury from being thrown from his horse, the details concernng the break up of Lewis and Margaret Meade's engagement and other related affairs, one involving Ben who had to flee the attentions of a girl already engaged in Halifax County where he first practiced medicine
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1834 January 7 (Box 3)
  writes concerning Ben doing well, his treatment of Septimia, James not doing well (died the 23rd), the sickness of two of Jane's slaves, Harriet and Sarah, and notes that they are still at Edgehill
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1834 January 23 (Box 3)
  sends news of the sickness of her children, Joseph's trip to Bombay, difficulties in the Coolidge family, and of Mary in good spirits and health
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1834 March 19 (Box 3)
  writes about Joseph's admission as a partner in the firm of Russell and Company as of January 1, which was promised to him when he was sent out to Bombay by Captain Augustine Heard and Mr. Lowe, the panic of the businessmen of Boston, the problems of the Coolidge family, the sickness of her children, and describes some of the gifts Joseph has sent to her from the Orient
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1834 April 15 (Box 3)
  writes of New England politics, mentions that Mr. Hart came by while in Boston trying to raise a subscription to purchase Monticello, refers to the trying conditions of the past winter, her expectation of a visit by Joseph in the summer of 1835, and speaks disparagingly of Walker Gilmer who will share duties with Jefferson in the next session of the Virginia Legislature
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1834 June 20 (Box 3)
  expresses her joy that Ellen has agreed to come and stay with Jane and Jefferson for a visit, assuring her that her family would not place too great a burden on Jefferson's family, makes arrangements for her to travel to Washington and stay at their home before she continues on to Edgehill, and mentions Ben's intention of marrying in the fall if Sally's [Sally Champe Carter] delicate health will allow it
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1835 May 6 (Box 3)
  describes her journey back to Boston as far as New York after her visit to Virginia and Washington, including her companions on the journey, her Aunt Hackley, comparing New York unfavorably with Philadelphia, and her shopping experiences, Ellen was apparently accompanied by her husband Joseph on a visit home from China (Joseph is mentioned several times in the letter)
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1835 May 24 (Box 3)
  informs her that they are on their way back to Washington but that Joseph must sail for Canton by the end of June, and that she will not accompany him but must remain in the United States to care for the children, expresses her dread at being separated from her husband, and reveals Joseph's plans to rent his father's house on Bowdoin Street for the family during his absence
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1835 September 27 (Box 3)
  discusses Virginia's decision to stay in Philadelphia where her children attend school while Nicholas travels to Havana, gives her advice about what clothes they will need for the winter, and mentions that Martha, Septimia, and Mary are visiting with her
- "Song from the Maid of the Mill" copied by Martha Jefferson Randolph [ante 1835] (Box 3)
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1836 April 26 (Box 3)
  furnishes details concerning her mother's health which make it difficult for her to travel yet, notes that Martha will probably travel with Mr. Heard to Philadelphia where Virginia is living, describes her summer plans to go to Newport, asks Virginia to stay with her at Newport, discusses Mrs. G. Lyman's family life, mentions the request of Nicholas for rocking chairs, supplies news of Joseph presently in Calcutta and Bengal where he must remain until June, mentions Septimia visiting at New Orleans, George in Lisbon in March, Lewis sick in Nashville and his recovery, and the birth of a son to Elizabeth Martin and Meriwether Lewis Randolph named Andrew Jackson Randolph Andrew born while Lewis was in Washington to report on Arkansan progress towards statehood
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1836 May 10 (Box 3)
  gives her the results of her trip to Newport, Rhode Island, where she ran into their kinsman Richard Kidder Randolph an inhabitant of Newport for twenty-six years, describes the lodgings he helped her find, asks Virginia to share them with her, mentions a letter from Septimia at Pensacola, Florida, the death of Lewis' mother-in-law Mrs. Martin just as he was to leave with his family for Little Rock, Arkansas, leaving behind several small children, Martha's plans to leave Boston by the middle of the month, and her disappointment in her matchmaking attempts between Mary and Mr. Heard
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1836 August 22 (Box 3)
  complains about the constant rain and flooding at Edgehill, mentions the birth of Isaetta Carter Randolph to Ben and Sarah, describes the fate of the three servants that gave them so much trouble when Ellen visited Edgehill, Critty, Harriet and Mary Ann, who were sent west for their misconduct, the relationship of deep affection and trust between Mary Ann and her new master, Cornelia's plans to stay at Edgehill for the winter, and Martha's concern for her, the letter of William [Randolph?] to Jefferson urging him to join him in a suit to set aside his father's cousin John Randolph's will of 1821 which emancipated his slaves, her disapproval of the idea because if the will were set aside the emancipation clause would be overturned, her disgust that they would bring in Mrs. Morris private correspondence with him and her past indiscretions, mentions that George is at the naval school in Norfolk preparing for his exam, talk of running Jefferson for Governor, and relates an untrue and unfavorable story printed about Jefferson last winter about the lengths to which he would go to secure a vote
- George Wythe Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1836 August 23 (Box 3)
  mentions his arrival from the Mediterranean on a merchant ship to sit for his examination, and asks for Lewis' address and his occupation now that Arkansas is a state, his letter was sent by Ellen to her mother with a note notifying Martha of their plans to leave Newport and to return to Boston and Philadelphia, and mentions the death of Mary Stearnes
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1836 September 6 (Box 3)
  mentions her plans to return to Boston, problems in securing servants, her receipt of letters from Joseph, missing Virginia's company, and news of their associates
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 February 8 (Box 3)
  expresses worry over their lack of correspondence since her departure for Havana with Cornelia and Septimia, Mary being with Ellen, mentions the death of Joseph's mother, trouble keeping their spirits up, and a letter of Joseph's from Singapore
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 February 22 (Box 3)
  reproves her sister for not writing to her, sends a letter and several gifts by Mr. Gorham, mentions [William Henry?] Furness' (1802-1896) remarks on the Gospels, asks about the health of Septimia, and her son Joseph who was also in Havana
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 March 23 (Box 3)
  mentions her receipt of several letters from Havana, Mary's health, the departure of Joseph's partner [John Murray] Forbes from the East for home, having to be satisfied with a fortune of $100,000, and retaining an interest in the firm, her uncertainty of when Joseph might return home, and Mr. Heard's popularity in Boston
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 April 6 (Box 3)
  voices her concern for her son in Cuba, mentions the horrible weather in Boston which was still in the grip of winter, and a letter from Joseph in which he has just commenced a term of a new partnership (with nearly the same partners) and bemoaning their long separation
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 May 13 (Box 3)
  writes concerning her poor health which is aggravated by the climate, her thankfulness that Virginia will keep her son Joseph longer, refers to the "Panic of 1837," her fear of Joseph losing this year's earnings, because no ship has sailed for the Canton trade from Boston, and mentions her household expenses in Boston
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 June 14 (Box 3)
  thanks her for the offer of letting her and her family live with them in Cuba but fears the trouble and expense of traveling there would be too much, mentions her search for a smaller, more reasonable house by next winter, relates an attempt of a group of arsonists to burn her house, resulting in the institution of a private neighborhood watch, describes a riot in Boston between the Irish and Americans, refers to Boston's suffering from the previous rage of speculation, and mentions the bankruptcy of Israel Thorndike
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 July 17 (Box 3)
  writes that she is unable to leave Boston for Havana as her father-in-law has just suffered a stroke
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 September 25 (Box 3)
  mentions her attempts to write to everyone before she sails for Canton, the health of her father-in-law, and her difficulties in heating her house
- Joseph Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1837 November 17 (Box 3)
  begs Virginia to visit them at Boston for her health in the spring, describes his plans to return to China to stay for an unknown period and mentions that Ellen might go with him
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1838 January 19 (Box 3)
  writes concerning her preparations to leave Boston, her poor health, her confusion over their plans and her dread of going to China
- Ellen Coolidge to Jane Randolph 1841 August 22 (Box 3)
  writes from Boston where she is leaving her country for the third time in four years, refers to her stay in Macao, mentions her anxiety concerning Virginia, rejoices in Ben's prosperity and the marriage of Jane's daughter Cary Anne [Randolph] to Francis Gildart Ruffin, who plan to reside at Shadwell, mentions George's success as a lawyer, relates the perils of her sea voyage, opportunities in the "celestial Empire," their share of the estate of Joseph's father, her intense longing to see her children at Monsieur Briquet's boarding school at Plainpalais, near Geneva, and the loss of Nicholas' place in Havana and his plans to live on a plantation in Cuba
- Ellen Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph 1841 August 30 (Box 3)
  refers to Joseph and her sailing for China in July 1839, their idea of involving George in a merchant career with the house of Augustine Heard and Company, relates in detail their plans for him if he is interested, even to the route to China via Geneva and Egypt, and mentions the opportunities and the risks of George trying his future in China, leaving it to Jeff's discretion
- Ellen Coolidge to Jane Randolph 1841 September 20 (Box 3)
  writes concerning their plans to sail from New York for the Havre on the Duchess of Orleans, her sympathy for Septimia, who has an infirm husband, two children and slender means, her plans for schooling her boys in Europe, and her desire not to influence George's decision over whether to join the Coolidges in China
- Ellen Coolidge to Jane Randolph 1843 May 17 (Box 3)
  writes from Geneva, plans to take Randolph to the Baths of [Lasey?] on the Rhone above the Lake of Geneva for his health, outlines the ineffective treatment for his increasing deafness, indicates her uncertainty about when she will return to America, notes that Joseph is detained in Canton, and makes an observation that women are treated better in the United States than anywhere abroad, especially after they are married, both under the law and by custom
- Ellen Coolidge to Jane Randolph 1844 August 1 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the arrival of Joseph in Geneva on May 29th, their departure for London, mentions that Randolph and Jefferson were sent with Browse Trist to a gymnasium in Dresden, Germany, kept by Dr. Blochman, Algernon and Sidney at school in Switzerland, their proposal to travel to the Continent, descend the Rhine, and go to Dresden to see their sons, her uncertainty about whether Joseph can help Jefferson Smith get into the China business as he has closed his concerns in China, gave up his business connections there, and left his former American partners, mentions that in Paris she was visited by the heirs of Lafayette who oppose the present French ruler, Louis Philippe, and describes the U.S. Minister to London, [Edward] Everett (1794-1865), and her dim view of the state of American politics
- Ellen Coolidge to Jefferson Randolph 1845 February 24 (Box 3)
  attributes the degradation of American politics to the leadership of the "unprincipled state of New York and the wicked city of New York" and the "unwise naturalization laws" which allow the lower classes of European immigrants to vote in political elections in the United States, mentions her horror at the proposal of non-payment of state debts and the justification of slavery in principle and its defence on any other terms than dire necessity, she relates that the United States has fallen into disrepute abroad, and suggests that her interest money be paid to Septimia
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist [1848?] May 29 (Box 3)
  arrives in New York and relates complaints from several gentlemen that American ladies are notorious for not expressing thanks for favors done for them such as escorting them on long journeys, and notes people she has visited in New York
- Ellen Coolidge to Henry S. Randall and others, 1845, 1856-1858 (Box 3)